<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monojit Choudhury | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/monojit-choudhury/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/monojit-choudhury/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Monojit Choudhury</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Monojit Choudhury</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/monojit-choudhury/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SMAB: MAB based word Sensitivity Estimation Framework and its Applications in Adversarial Text Generation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/smab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/smab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To understand the complexity of sequence classification tasks, Hahn et al. (2021) proposed sensitivity as the number of disjoint subsets of the input sequence that can each be individually changed to change the output. Though effective, calculating sensitivity at scale using this framework is costly because of exponential time complexity. Therefore, we introduce a Sensitivity-based Multi-Armed Bandit framework (SMAB), which provides a scalable approach for calculating word-level local (sentence-level) and global (aggregated) sensitivities concerning an underlying text classifier for any dataset. We establish the effectiveness of our approach through various applications. We perform a case study on CHECKLIST generated sentiment analysis dataset where we show that our algorithm indeed captures intuitively high and low-sensitive words. Through experiments on multiple tasks and languages, we show that sensitivity can serve as a proxy for accuracy in the absence of gold data. Lastly, we show that guiding perturbation prompts using sensitivity values in adversarial example generation improves attack success rate by 15.58%, whereas using sensitivity as an additional reward in adversarial paraphrase generation gives a 12.00% improvement over SOTA approaches. Warning: Contains potentially offensive content.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tricking LLMs into Disobedience: Understanding, Analyzing, and Preventing Jailbreaks</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/promptinj/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/promptinj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent explorations with commercial Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown that non-expert users can jailbreak LLMs by simply manipulating the prompts; resulting in degenerate output behavior, privacy and security breaches, offensive outputs, and violations of content regulator policies. Limited formal studies have been carried out to formalize and analyze these attacks and their mitigations. We bridge this gap by proposing a formalism and a taxonomy of known (and possible) jailbreaks. We perform a survey of existing jailbreak methods and their effectiveness on open-source and commercial LLMs (such as GPT 3.5, OPT, BLOOM, and FLAN-T5-xxl). We further propose a limited set of prompt guards and discuss their effectiveness against known attack types.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prover: Generating Intermediate Steps for NLI with Commonsense Knowledge Retrieval and Next-Step Prediction</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/multihop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/multihop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Natural Language Inference (NLI) task often requires reasoning over multiple steps to reach the conclusion. While the necessity of generating such intermediate steps (instead of a summary explanation) has gained popular support, it is unclear how to generate such steps without complete end-to-end supervision and how such generated steps can be further utilized. In this work, we train and enhance a sequence-to-sequence next-step prediction model with external commonsense knowledge and search to generate intermediate steps with limited next-step supervision. We show the correctness of such generated steps through human verification, on MNLI and MED datasets (and discuss the limitations through qualitative examples). We show that such generated steps can help improve end-to-end NLI task performance using simple data augmentation strategies. Using a CheckList dataset for NLI, we also explore the effect of augmentation on specific reasoning types.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LoNLI: An Extensible Framework for Testing Diverse Logical Reasoning Capabilities for NLI</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/lonli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/lonli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Natural Language Inference (NLI) is considered a representative task to test natural language understanding (NLU).  In this work, we propose an extensible framework to collectively yet categorically test diverse Logical reasoning capabilities required for NLI (and by extension, NLU). Motivated by behavioral testing, we create a semi-synthetic large test-bench (363 templates, 363k examples) and an associated framework that offers following utilities: 1) individually test and analyze reasoning capabilities along 17 reasoning dimensions (including pragmatic reasoning), 2) design experiments to study cross-capability information content (leave one out or bring one in); and 3) the synthetic nature enable us to control for artifacts and biases. We extend a publicly available framework of automated test case instantiation from free-form natural language templates (CheckList), and a well-defined taxonomy of capabilities to cover a wide range of increasingly harder test cases while varying the complexity of natural language. Through our analysis of state-of-the-art NLI systems, we observe that our benchmark is indeed hard (and non-trivial even with training on additional resources). Some capabilities stand out as harder. Further fine-grained analysis and fine-tuning experiments reveal more insights about these capabilities and the models &amp;ndash; supporting and extending previous observations; thus showing the utility of the proposed testbench.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilingual CheckList: Generation and Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/amcg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/amcg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recently proposed CheckList (Riberio et al,. 2020) approach to evaluation of NLP systems has revealed high failure rates for basic capabilities for multiple state-of-the-art and commercial models. However, the CheckList creation process is manual which creates a bottleneck towards creation of multilingual CheckLists catering 100s of languages. In this work, we explore multiple approaches to generate and evaluate the quality of Multilingual CheckList. We device an algorithm &amp;ndash; Automated Multilingual Checklist Generation (AMCG) for automatically transferring a CheckList from a source to a target language that relies on a reasonable machine translation system. We then compare the CheckList generated by AMCG with CheckLists generated with different levels of human intervention. Through in-depth crosslingual experiments between English and Hindi, and broad multilingual experiments spanning 11 languages, we show that the automatic approach can provide accurate estimates of failure rates of a model across capabilities, as would a human-verified CheckList, and better than CheckLists generated by humans from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vector Space Interpolation for Query Expansion</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/interpolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/interpolation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Topic-sensitive query set expansion is an important area of research that aims to improve search results for information retrieval. It is particularly crucial for queries related to sensitive and emerging topics. In this work, we describe a method for query set expansion about emerging topics using vector space interpolation. We use a transformer model called OPTIMUS, which is suitable for vector space manipulation due to its variational autoencoder nature. One of our proposed methods – Dirichlet interpolation shows promising results for query expansion. Our methods effectively generate new queries about the sensitive topic by incorporating set-level diversity, which is not captured by traditional sentence-level augmentation methods such as paraphrasing or back-translation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LITMUS Predictor: An AI Assistant for Building Reliable, High-Performing and Fair Multilingual NLP Systems</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/litmus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/litmus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pre-trained multilingual language models are gaining popularity due to their cross-lingual zero-shot transfer ability, but these models do not perform equally well in all languages. Evaluating task-specific performance of a model in a large number of languages is often a challenge due to lack of labeled data, as is targeting improvements in low performing languages through few-shot learning. We present a tool - LITMUS Predictor - that can make reliable performance projections for a fine-tuned task-specific model in a set of languages without test and training data, and help strategize data labeling efforts to optimize performance and fairness objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Effects of Reasoning Types on Cross-Lingual Transfer Performance</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/crosslingual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/crosslingual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Multilingual language models achieve impressive zero-shot accuracies in many languages in complex tasks such as Natural Language Inference (NLI). Examples in NLI (and equivalent complex tasks) often pertain to various types of sub-tasks, requiring different kinds of reasoning. Certain types of reasoning have proven to be more difficult to learn in a monolingual context, and in the crosslingual context, similar observations may shed light on zero-shot transfer efficiency and few-shot sample selection. Hence, to investigate the effects of types of reasoning on transfer performance, we propose a category-annotated multilingual NLI dataset.  We discuss the challenges to scale monolingual annotations to multiple languages. We statistically observe interesting effects that the confluence of reasoning types and language similarities have on transfer performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trusting RoBERTa over BERT: Insights from CheckListing the Natural Language Inference Task</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/checklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recent state-of-the-art natural language understanding (NLU) systems often behave unpredictably, failing on simpler reasoning examples. Despite this, there has been limited focus on quantifying progress towards systems with more predictable behavior. We think that reasoning capability-wise behavioral summary (proposed in Ribeiro et al. (2020)) is a step towards bridging this gap. We create a CHECKLIST test-suite (184K examples) for the Natural Language Inference (NLI) task, a representative NLU task. We benchmark state-of-the-art NLI systems on this test-suite, which reveals fine-grained insights into the reasoning abilities of BERT and RoBERTa. Our analysis further reveals inconsistencies of the models on examples derived from the same template or distinct templates but pertaining to same reasoning capability, indicating that generalizing the models’ behavior through observations made on a CheckList is non-trivial. Through an user-study, we find that users were able to utilize behavioral information to generalize much better for examples predicted from RoBERTa, compared to that of BERT.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TaxiNLI: Taking a Ride up the NLU Hill</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/taxinli/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/taxinli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pre-trained Transformer-based neural architectures have consistently achieved state-of-the-art performance in the Natural Language Inference (NLI) task. Since NLI examples encompass a variety of linguistic, logical, and reasoning phenomena, it remains unclear as to which specific concepts are learnt by the trained systems and where they can achieve strong generalization. To investigate this question, we propose a taxonomic hierarchy of categories that are relevant for the NLI task. We introduce TAXINLI, a new dataset, that has 10k examples from the MNLI dataset (Williams et al., 2018) with these taxonomic labels. Through various experiments on TAXINLI, we observe that whereas for certain taxonomic categories SOTA neural models have achieved near perfect accuracies - a large jump over the previous models - some categories still remain difficult. Our work adds to the growing body of literature that shows the gaps in the current NLI systems and datasets through a systematic presentation and analysis of reasoning categories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
