<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vision and Language | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/tags/vision-and-language/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/tags/vision-and-language/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Vision and Language</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Vision and Language</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/tags/vision-and-language/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vision and Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/project/vision/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/project/vision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many vision and language tasks require commonsense reasoning beyond data-driven image and natural language processing. Cognitive Sciences and Active Vision literature points to an explicit iterative interaction
among perception, reasoning, and memeory (knowledge) modules (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.public.asu.edu/~cbaral/papers/acs2016.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DeepIU ACS 2015&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt; Captioning &lt;/h3&gt;
In our earliest attempt (&lt;a href=&#34;https://imagesdg.wordpress.com/image-to-scene-description-graph/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CVIU 2017&lt;/a&gt; ), we used a combination of image classification, reasoning with commonsense knowledge (extracted from training captions) to propose a Scene Description Graph as an intermediate representation for a natural image. We showed the efficacy of this representation through image captioning, image retrieval tasks (and QA case studies.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt; Visual QA, Image Puzzles and Visual Reasoning &lt;/h3&gt;
We have proposed instantiations of this abstract architecture to solve image puzzles, VQA and visual reasoning tasks such as CLEVR. In our &lt;a href=&#34;https://visionandreasoning.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;AAAI 2018 VQA&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://imageriddle.wordpress.com/imageriddle/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UAI 2018 Puzzles&lt;/a&gt; work, we have proposed an explicit probabilistic soft logic layer on top of a neural architecture that helps integrate commonsense knowledge and induces post-hoc interpretability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on, for an end-to-end (differentiable) integration of spatial knowledge, we explore a combination of knowledge distillation, probabilistic logic, and relational network in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.public.asu.edu/~cbaral/papers/2019-wacv.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;WACV 2019 CLEVR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;References&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; overflow-y: hidden;&#34; class=&#34;wcustomhtml&#34;&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;margin-bottom:0px;&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr style=&#34;float: center&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt; 
&lt;li&gt; 
Somak Aditya, Yezhou Yang, Chitta Baral. Integrating Knowledge and Reasoning in Image Understanding. IJCAI 2019. 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Rudra Saha, Yezhou Yang and Chitta Baral. Spatial Knowledge Distillation to aid Visual Reasoning. WACV 2019. 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Yezhou Yang, Chitta Baral. Explicit Reasoning over End-to-End Neural Architectures for Visual Question Answering. AAAI 2018.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Yezhou Yang, Chitta Baral and Yiannis Aloimonos. Combining Knowledge and Reasoning through Probabilistic Soft Logic for Image Puzzle Solving. UAI 2018.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Yezhou Yang, Chitta Baral, Yiannis Aloimonos and Cornelia Fermuller. Image Understanding using Vision and Reasoning through Scene Description Graph. Computer Vision and Image Understanding Journal. (Accepted December 2017)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Yezhou Yang, Chitta Baral and Yiannis Aloimonos. Answering Image Riddles using Vision and Reasoning through Probabilistic Soft Logic.. Arxiv version. 2016. Website with additional information on this work.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Chitta Baral, Yezhou Yang, Yiannnis Aloimonos and Cornelia Fermuller. DeepIU: An architecture for image understanding. Advances in Cognitive Systems. 2016.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Yezhou Yang, Chitta Baral, Cornelia Fermuller, Yiannis Aloimonos. From Images to Sentences through Scene Description Graphs using Commonsense Reasoning and Knowledge. Arxiv version.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Somak Aditya, Yiannis Aloimonos, Chitta Baral, Cornelia Fermuller and Yezhou Yang. Visual common-sense for scene understanding using perception, semantic parsing and reasoning. Common-sense 2015, AAAI 2015 Spring Symposium. (Appenidix with code.)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt; --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
