<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Soujanya Poria | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/soujanya-poria/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/soujanya-poria/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Soujanya Poria</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Soujanya Poria</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/soujanya-poria/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>STUCK IN THE QUICKSAND OF NUMERACY, FAR FROM AGI SUMMIT: EVALUATING LLMS&#39; MATHEMATICAL COMPETENCY THROUGH ONTOLOGY-GUIDED PERTURBATIONS</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/more24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/more24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) have showcased striking results on existing logical reasoning benchmarks, with some models even surpassing human performance. However, the true depth of their competencies and robustness, in mathematical reasoning tasks, remains an open question. In response, we develop (i) an ontology of perturbations of maths questions, (ii) a semi-automatic method of perturbation, and (iii) a dataset of perturbed maths questions
to probe the limits of LLM capabilities in mathematical-reasoning tasks.
These controlled perturbations span across multiple fine dimensions of the structural and representational aspects of maths questions. Using GPT-4, we generated the &lt;span style=&#34;font-variant-caps: small-caps&#34;&gt;More&lt;/span&gt; dataset by perturbing randomly selected five seed questions from GSM8K. This process was guided by our ontology and involved a thorough automatic and manual filtering process, yielding a set of 216 maths problems.
We conducted comprehensive evaluation of both closed-source and open-source LLMs on &lt;span style=&#34;font-variant-caps: small-caps&#34;&gt;More&lt;/span&gt;. The results show a significant performance drop across all the models against the perturbed questions. This strongly suggests that current LLMs lack robust mathematical skills and a deep understanding of reasoning. This research not only identifies multiple gaps in the capabilities of current models, but also highlights multiple potential directions for future development. Our dataset will be made publicly available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/datasets/declare-lab/GSM8k_MORE&#34;&gt;huggingface library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Robust Information-Masking Approach for Domain Counterfactual Generation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/counterfactualda/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/counterfactualda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Domain shift is a big challenge in NLP, thus, many approaches resort to learning domain-invariant features to mitigate the inference phase domain shift. Such methods, however, fail to leverage the domain-specific nuances relevant to the task at hand. To avoid such drawbacks, domain counterfactual generation aims to transform a text from the source domain to a given target domain. However, due to the limited availability of data, such frequency-based methods often miss and lead to some valid and spurious domain-token associations. Hence, we employ a three-step domain obfuscation approach that involves frequency and attention norm-based masking, to mask domain-specific cues, and unmasking to regain the domain generic context. Our experiments empirically show that the counterfactual samples sourced from our masked text lead to improved domain transfer on 10 out of 12 domain sentiment classification settings, with an average of 2% accuracy improvement over the state-of-the-art for unsupervised domain adaptation (UDA). Further our model outperforms the state-of-the-art by achieving 1.4% average accuracy improvement in the adversarial domain adaptation (ADA) setting. Moreover, our model also shows its domain adaptation efficacy on a large multi-domain intent classification dataset where it attains state-of-the-art results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
