<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nguyen Ha Vo | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/nguyen-ha-vo/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/nguyen-ha-vo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Nguyen Ha Vo</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Nguyen Ha Vo</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/nguyen-ha-vo/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Addressing the Winograd Schema Challenge-Building and Using a Semantic Parser and a Knowledge Hunting Module.</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/kparser/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/kparser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Concerned about the Turing test’s ability to correctly
evaluate if a system exhibits human-like intelligence,
the Winograd Schema Challenge (WSC)
has been proposed as an alternative. A Winograd
Schema consists of a sentence and a question. The
answers to the questions are intuitive for humans
but are designed to be difficult for machines, as
they require various forms of commonsense knowledge
about the sentence. In this paper we demonstrate
our progress towards addressing the WSC.
We present an approach that identifies the knowledge
needed to answer a challenge question, hunts
down that knowledge from text repositories, and
then reasons with them to come up with the answer.
In the process we develop a semantic parser
(&lt;a href=&#34;www.kparser.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;www.kparser.org&lt;/a&gt;). We show that our approach
works well with respect to a subset of Winograd
schemas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying various kinds of event mentions in k-parser output</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/identifying/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/identifying/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we show how our semantic parser (Knowledge Parser or K-Parser) identifies various kinds of event mentions in the input text. The types include recursive (complex) and non recursive event mentions. K-Parser outputs each event mention in form of an acyclic graph with root nodes as the verbs that drive those events. The children nodes of the verbs represent the entities participating in the events, and their conceptual classes. The on-line demo of the system is available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://kparser.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://kparser.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
