<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aalok Sathe | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/aalok-sathe/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/aalok-sathe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Aalok Sathe</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Aalok Sathe</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/aalok-sathe/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Effects of Reasoning Types on Cross-Lingual Transfer Performance</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/crosslingual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/crosslingual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Multilingual language models achieve impressive zero-shot accuracies in many languages in complex tasks such as Natural Language Inference (NLI). Examples in NLI (and equivalent complex tasks) often pertain to various types of sub-tasks, requiring different kinds of reasoning. Certain types of reasoning have proven to be more difficult to learn in a monolingual context, and in the crosslingual context, similar observations may shed light on zero-shot transfer efficiency and few-shot sample selection. Hence, to investigate the effects of types of reasoning on transfer performance, we propose a category-annotated multilingual NLI dataset.  We discuss the challenges to scale monolingual annotations to multiple languages. We statistically observe interesting effects that the confluence of reasoning types and language similarities have on transfer performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TaxiNLI: Taking a Ride up the NLU Hill</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/taxinli/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/taxinli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pre-trained Transformer-based neural architectures have consistently achieved state-of-the-art performance in the Natural Language Inference (NLI) task. Since NLI examples encompass a variety of linguistic, logical, and reasoning phenomena, it remains unclear as to which specific concepts are learnt by the trained systems and where they can achieve strong generalization. To investigate this question, we propose a taxonomic hierarchy of categories that are relevant for the NLI task. We introduce TAXINLI, a new dataset, that has 10k examples from the MNLI dataset (Williams et al., 2018) with these taxonomic labels. Through various experiments on TAXINLI, we observe that whereas for certain taxonomic categories SOTA neural models have achieved near perfect accuracies - a large jump over the previous models - some categories still remain difficult. Our work adds to the growing body of literature that shows the gaps in the current NLI systems and datasets through a systematic presentation and analysis of reasoning categories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
