<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Navin Goyal | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/navin-goyal/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/navin-goyal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Navin Goyal</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Navin Goyal</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/navin-goyal/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Nuances of Transformers&#39; Polynomial Simplification Abilities</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/polysimp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/polysimp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Symbolic Mathematical tasks such as integration often require multiple welldefined steps and understanding of sub-tasks to reach a solution. To understand Transformers’ abilities in such tasks in a fine-grained manner, we deviate from traditional end-to-end settings, and explore a step-wise polynomial simplification task. Polynomials can be written in a simple normal form as a sum of monomials which are ordered in a lexicographic order. For a polynomial which is not necessarily in this normal form, a sequence of simplification steps is applied to reach the fully simplified (i.e., in the normal form) polynomial. We propose a synthetic Polynomial dataset generation algorithm that generates polynomials with unique proof steps. Through varying coefficient configurations, input representation, proof granularity, and extensive hyper-parameter tuning, we observe that Transformers consistently struggle with numeric multiplication. We explore two ways to mitigate this: Curriculum Learning and a Symbolic Calculator approach (where the numeric operations are offloaded to a calculator). Both approaches provide significant gains over the vanilla Transformers-based baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
