<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>3 | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/publication_types/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>3</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>STUCK IN THE QUICKSAND OF NUMERACY, FAR FROM AGI SUMMIT: EVALUATING LLMS&#39; MATHEMATICAL COMPETENCY THROUGH ONTOLOGY-GUIDED PERTURBATIONS</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/more24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/more24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) have showcased striking results on existing logical reasoning benchmarks, with some models even surpassing human performance. However, the true depth of their competencies and robustness, in mathematical reasoning tasks, remains an open question. In response, we develop (i) an ontology of perturbations of maths questions, (ii) a semi-automatic method of perturbation, and (iii) a dataset of perturbed maths questions
to probe the limits of LLM capabilities in mathematical-reasoning tasks.
These controlled perturbations span across multiple fine dimensions of the structural and representational aspects of maths questions. Using GPT-4, we generated the &lt;span style=&#34;font-variant-caps: small-caps&#34;&gt;More&lt;/span&gt; dataset by perturbing randomly selected five seed questions from GSM8K. This process was guided by our ontology and involved a thorough automatic and manual filtering process, yielding a set of 216 maths problems.
We conducted comprehensive evaluation of both closed-source and open-source LLMs on &lt;span style=&#34;font-variant-caps: small-caps&#34;&gt;More&lt;/span&gt;. The results show a significant performance drop across all the models against the perturbed questions. This strongly suggests that current LLMs lack robust mathematical skills and a deep understanding of reasoning. This research not only identifies multiple gaps in the capabilities of current models, but also highlights multiple potential directions for future development. Our dataset will be made publicly available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/datasets/declare-lab/GSM8k_MORE&#34;&gt;huggingface library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SMAB: MAB based word Sensitivity Estimation Framework and its Applications in Adversarial Text Generation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/smab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/smab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To understand the complexity of sequence classification tasks, Hahn et al. (2021) proposed sensitivity as the number of disjoint subsets of the input sequence that can each be individually changed to change the output. Though effective, calculating sensitivity at scale using this framework is costly because of exponential time complexity. Therefore, we introduce a Sensitivity-based Multi-Armed Bandit framework (SMAB), which provides a scalable approach for calculating word-level local (sentence-level) and global (aggregated) sensitivities concerning an underlying text classifier for any dataset. We establish the effectiveness of our approach through various applications. We perform a case study on CHECKLIST generated sentiment analysis dataset where we show that our algorithm indeed captures intuitively high and low-sensitive words. Through experiments on multiple tasks and languages, we show that sensitivity can serve as a proxy for accuracy in the absence of gold data. Lastly, we show that guiding perturbation prompts using sensitivity values in adversarial example generation improves attack success rate by 15.58%, whereas using sensitivity as an additional reward in adversarial paraphrase generation gives a 12.00% improvement over SOTA approaches. Warning: Contains potentially offensive content.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code Prompting Elicits Conditional Reasoning Abilities in Text&#43; Code LLMs</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/codeprompting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/codeprompting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reasoning is a fundamental component for achieving language understanding. Among the multiple types of reasoning, conditional reasoning, the ability to draw different conclusions depending on some condition, has been understudied in large language models (LLMs). Recent prompting methods, such as chain of thought, have significantly improved LLMs on reasoning tasks. Nevertheless, there is still little understanding of what triggers reasoning abilities in LLMs. We hypothesize that code prompts can trigger conditional reasoning in LLMs trained on text and code. We propose a chain of prompts that transforms a natural language problem into code and prompts the LLM with the generated code. Our experiments find that code prompts exhibit a performance boost between 2.6 and 7.7 points on GPT 3.5 across multiple datasets requiring conditional reasoning. We then conduct experiments to discover how code prompts elicit conditional reasoning abilities and through which features. We observe that prompts need to contain natural language text accompanied by high-quality code that closely represents the semantics of the instance text. Furthermore, we show that code prompts are more efficient, requiring fewer demonstrations, and that they trigger superior state tracking of variables or key entities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERVQA: A Dataset to Benchmark the Readiness of Large Vision Language Models in Hospital Environments</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/ervqa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/ervqa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The global shortage of healthcare workers has demanded the development of smart healthcare assistants, which can help monitor and alert healthcare workers when necessary. We examine the healthcare knowledge of existing Large Vision Language Models (LVLMs) via the Visual Question Answering (VQA) task in hospital settings through expert annotated open-ended questions. We introduce the Emergency Room Visual Question Answering (ERVQA) dataset, consisting of 790 &lt;image, question, answer&gt; triplets covering diverse emergency room scenarios, a seminal benchmark for LVLMs. By developing a detailed error taxonomy and analyzing answer trends, we reveal the nuanced nature of the task. We benchmark state-of-the-art open-source and closed LVLMs using traditional and adapted VQA metrics: Entailment Score and CLIPScore Confidence. Analyzing errors across models, we infer trends based on properties like decoder type, model size, and in-context examples. Our findings suggest the ERVQA dataset presents a highly complex task, highlighting the need for specialized, domain-specific solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text2Afford: Probing Object Affordance Prediction abilities of Language Models solely from Text</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/text2afford/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/text2afford/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We investigate the knowledge of object affordances in pre-trained language models
(LMs) and pre-trained Vision-Language models (VLMs). A growing body of literature
shows that PTLMs fail inconsistently and nonintuitively, demonstrating a lack of reasoning
and grounding. To take a first step toward quantifying the effect of grounding (or lack thereof),
we curate a novel and comprehensive dataset of object affordances – TEXT2AFFORD, characterized by 15 affordance classes. Unlike affordance datasets collected in vision and language domains, we annotate in-the-wild sentences with objects and affordances. Experimental results reveal that PTLMs exhibit limited reasoning abilities when it comes to uncommon object affordances. We also observe that pretrained VLMs do not necessarily capture object affordances effectively. Through few-shot fine-tuning, we demonstrate improvement in affordance knowledge in PTLMs and VLMs.
Our research contributes a novel dataset for language grounding tasks, and presents insights
into LM capabilities, advancing the understanding of object affordances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trusting RoBERTa over BERT: Insights from CheckListing the Natural Language Inference Task</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/checklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recent state-of-the-art natural language understanding (NLU) systems often behave unpredictably, failing on simpler reasoning examples. Despite this, there has been limited focus on quantifying progress towards systems with more predictable behavior. We think that reasoning capability-wise behavioral summary (proposed in Ribeiro et al. (2020)) is a step towards bridging this gap. We create a CHECKLIST test-suite (184K examples) for the Natural Language Inference (NLI) task, a representative NLU task. We benchmark state-of-the-art NLI systems on this test-suite, which reveals fine-grained insights into the reasoning abilities of BERT and RoBERTa. Our analysis further reveals inconsistencies of the models on examples derived from the same template or distinct templates but pertaining to same reasoning capability, indicating that generalizing the models’ behavior through observations made on a CheckList is non-trivial. Through an user-study, we find that users were able to utilize behavioral information to generalize much better for examples predicted from RoBERTa, compared to that of BERT.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
