<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>3 | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/publication_types/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>3</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>STUCK IN THE QUICKSAND OF NUMERACY, FAR FROM AGI SUMMIT: EVALUATING LLMS&#39; MATHEMATICAL COMPETENCY THROUGH ONTOLOGY-GUIDED PERTURBATIONS</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/more24/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/more24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) have showcased striking results on existing logical reasoning benchmarks, with some models even surpassing human performance. However, the true depth of their competencies and robustness, in mathematical reasoning tasks, remains an open question. In response, we develop (i) an ontology of perturbations of maths questions, (ii) a semi-automatic method of perturbation, and (iii) a dataset of perturbed maths questions
to probe the limits of LLM capabilities in mathematical-reasoning tasks.
These controlled perturbations span across multiple fine dimensions of the structural and representational aspects of maths questions. Using GPT-4, we generated the &lt;span style=&#34;font-variant-caps: small-caps&#34;&gt;More&lt;/span&gt; dataset by perturbing randomly selected five seed questions from GSM8K. This process was guided by our ontology and involved a thorough automatic and manual filtering process, yielding a set of 216 maths problems.
We conducted comprehensive evaluation of both closed-source and open-source LLMs on &lt;span style=&#34;font-variant-caps: small-caps&#34;&gt;More&lt;/span&gt;. The results show a significant performance drop across all the models against the perturbed questions. This strongly suggests that current LLMs lack robust mathematical skills and a deep understanding of reasoning. This research not only identifies multiple gaps in the capabilities of current models, but also highlights multiple potential directions for future development. Our dataset will be made publicly available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/datasets/declare-lab/GSM8k_MORE&#34;&gt;huggingface library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prover: Generating Intermediate Steps for NLI with Commonsense Knowledge Retrieval and Next-Step Prediction</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/multihop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/multihop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Natural Language Inference (NLI) task often requires reasoning over multiple steps to reach the conclusion. While the necessity of generating such intermediate steps (instead of a summary explanation) has gained popular support, it is unclear how to generate such steps without complete end-to-end supervision and how such generated steps can be further utilized. In this work, we train and enhance a sequence-to-sequence next-step prediction model with external commonsense knowledge and search to generate intermediate steps with limited next-step supervision. We show the correctness of such generated steps through human verification, on MNLI and MED datasets (and discuss the limitations through qualitative examples). We show that such generated steps can help improve end-to-end NLI task performance using simple data augmentation strategies. Using a CheckList dataset for NLI, we also explore the effect of augmentation on specific reasoning types.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SYNC: A Structurally guided Hard Negative Curricula for Efficient Neural Code Search</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/sync/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/sync/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In neural code search, a Transformers-based pre-trained language model (such as CodeBERT) is used to embed both the query (NL) and the code snippet (PL) into a joint representation space; which is used to retrieve the relevant PLs satisfying the query. These models often make mistakes such as retrieving snippets with incorrect data types, and incorrect method names or signatures. The generalization ability beyond training data is also limited (as the code retrieval datasets vary in the ways NL-PL pairs are collected). In this work, we propose a novel contrastive learning technique (SYNC) that enables efficient finetuning of code LMs with soft and hard negatives, where the hard negatives are constructed using a set of structure-aware AST-based perturbations; targeted towards possible syntactic and semantic variations.
Our method achieves significant improvements in retrieval performance for three code LMs (CodeBERT, GraphCodeBERT, UniXCoder) over four Python code retrieval datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tricking LLMs into Disobedience: Understanding, Analyzing, and Preventing Jailbreaks</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/promptinj/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/promptinj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent explorations with commercial Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown that non-expert users can jailbreak LLMs by simply manipulating the prompts; resulting in degenerate output behavior, privacy and security breaches, offensive outputs, and violations of content regulator policies. Limited formal studies have been carried out to formalize and analyze these attacks and their mitigations. We bridge this gap by proposing a formalism and a taxonomy of known (and possible) jailbreaks. We perform a survey of existing jailbreak methods and their effectiveness on open-source and commercial LLMs (such as GPT 3.5, OPT, BLOOM, and FLAN-T5-xxl). We further propose a limited set of prompt guards and discuss their effectiveness against known attack types.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Robust Information-Masking Approach for Domain Counterfactual Generation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/counterfactualda/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/counterfactualda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Domain shift is a big challenge in NLP, thus, many approaches resort to learning domain-invariant features to mitigate the inference phase domain shift. Such methods, however, fail to leverage the domain-specific nuances relevant to the task at hand. To avoid such drawbacks, domain counterfactual generation aims to transform a text from the source domain to a given target domain. However, due to the limited availability of data, such frequency-based methods often miss and lead to some valid and spurious domain-token associations. Hence, we employ a three-step domain obfuscation approach that involves frequency and attention norm-based masking, to mask domain-specific cues, and unmasking to regain the domain generic context. Our experiments empirically show that the counterfactual samples sourced from our masked text lead to improved domain transfer on 10 out of 12 domain sentiment classification settings, with an average of 2% accuracy improvement over the state-of-the-art for unsupervised domain adaptation (UDA). Further our model outperforms the state-of-the-art by achieving 1.4% average accuracy improvement in the adversarial domain adaptation (ADA) setting. Moreover, our model also shows its domain adaptation efficacy on a large multi-domain intent classification dataset where it attains state-of-the-art results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilingual CheckList: Generation and Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/amcg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/amcg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recently proposed CheckList (Riberio et al,. 2020) approach to evaluation of NLP systems has revealed high failure rates for basic capabilities for multiple state-of-the-art and commercial models. However, the CheckList creation process is manual which creates a bottleneck towards creation of multilingual CheckLists catering 100s of languages. In this work, we explore multiple approaches to generate and evaluate the quality of Multilingual CheckList. We device an algorithm &amp;ndash; Automated Multilingual Checklist Generation (AMCG) for automatically transferring a CheckList from a source to a target language that relies on a reasonable machine translation system. We then compare the CheckList generated by AMCG with CheckLists generated with different levels of human intervention. Through in-depth crosslingual experiments between English and Hindi, and broad multilingual experiments spanning 11 languages, we show that the automatic approach can provide accurate estimates of failure rates of a model across capabilities, as would a human-verified CheckList, and better than CheckLists generated by humans from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vector Space Interpolation for Query Expansion</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/interpolation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/interpolation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Topic-sensitive query set expansion is an important area of research that aims to improve search results for information retrieval. It is particularly crucial for queries related to sensitive and emerging topics. In this work, we describe a method for query set expansion about emerging topics using vector space interpolation. We use a transformer model called OPTIMUS, which is suitable for vector space manipulation due to its variational autoencoder nature. One of our proposed methods – Dirichlet interpolation shows promising results for query expansion. Our methods effectively generate new queries about the sensitive topic by incorporating set-level diversity, which is not captured by traditional sentence-level augmentation methods such as paraphrasing or back-translation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trusting RoBERTa over BERT: Insights from CheckListing the Natural Language Inference Task</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/checklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recent state-of-the-art natural language understanding (NLU) systems often behave unpredictably, failing on simpler reasoning examples. Despite this, there has been limited focus on quantifying progress towards systems with more predictable behavior. We think that reasoning capability-wise behavioral summary (proposed in Ribeiro et al. (2020)) is a step towards bridging this gap. We create a CHECKLIST test-suite (184K examples) for the Natural Language Inference (NLI) task, a representative NLU task. We benchmark state-of-the-art NLI systems on this test-suite, which reveals fine-grained insights into the reasoning abilities of BERT and RoBERTa. Our analysis further reveals inconsistencies of the models on examples derived from the same template or distinct templates but pertaining to same reasoning capability, indicating that generalizing the models’ behavior through observations made on a CheckList is non-trivial. Through an user-study, we find that users were able to utilize behavioral information to generalize much better for examples predicted from RoBERTa, compared to that of BERT.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
