<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Karthikeyan K | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/karthikeyan-k/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/karthikeyan-k/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Karthikeyan K</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Karthikeyan K</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/karthikeyan-k/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilingual CheckList: Generation and Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/amcg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/amcg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recently proposed CheckList (Riberio et al,. 2020) approach to evaluation of NLP systems has revealed high failure rates for basic capabilities for multiple state-of-the-art and commercial models. However, the CheckList creation process is manual which creates a bottleneck towards creation of multilingual CheckLists catering 100s of languages. In this work, we explore multiple approaches to generate and evaluate the quality of Multilingual CheckList. We device an algorithm &amp;ndash; Automated Multilingual Checklist Generation (AMCG) for automatically transferring a CheckList from a source to a target language that relies on a reasonable machine translation system. We then compare the CheckList generated by AMCG with CheckLists generated with different levels of human intervention. Through in-depth crosslingual experiments between English and Hindi, and broad multilingual experiments spanning 11 languages, we show that the automatic approach can provide accurate estimates of failure rates of a model across capabilities, as would a human-verified CheckList, and better than CheckLists generated by humans from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Effects of Reasoning Types on Cross-Lingual Transfer Performance</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/crosslingual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/crosslingual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Multilingual language models achieve impressive zero-shot accuracies in many languages in complex tasks such as Natural Language Inference (NLI). Examples in NLI (and equivalent complex tasks) often pertain to various types of sub-tasks, requiring different kinds of reasoning. Certain types of reasoning have proven to be more difficult to learn in a monolingual context, and in the crosslingual context, similar observations may shed light on zero-shot transfer efficiency and few-shot sample selection. Hence, to investigate the effects of types of reasoning on transfer performance, we propose a category-annotated multilingual NLI dataset.  We discuss the challenges to scale monolingual annotations to multiple languages. We statistically observe interesting effects that the confluence of reasoning types and language similarities have on transfer performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
