<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daivik Agarwal | Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/daivik-agarwal/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/daivik-agarwal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Daivik Agarwal</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://adityasomak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Daivik Agarwal</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/authors/daivik-agarwal/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text2Afford: Probing Object Affordance Prediction abilities of Language Models solely from Text</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/text2afford/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/text2afford/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We investigate the knowledge of object affordances in pre-trained language models
(LMs) and pre-trained Vision-Language models (VLMs). A growing body of literature
shows that PTLMs fail inconsistently and nonintuitively, demonstrating a lack of reasoning
and grounding. To take a first step toward quantifying the effect of grounding (or lack thereof),
we curate a novel and comprehensive dataset of object affordances – TEXT2AFFORD, characterized by 15 affordance classes. Unlike affordance datasets collected in vision and language domains, we annotate in-the-wild sentences with objects and affordances. Experimental results reveal that PTLMs exhibit limited reasoning abilities when it comes to uncommon object affordances. We also observe that pretrained VLMs do not necessarily capture object affordances effectively. Through few-shot fine-tuning, we demonstrate improvement in affordance knowledge in PTLMs and VLMs.
Our research contributes a novel dataset for language grounding tasks, and presents insights
into LM capabilities, advancing the understanding of object affordances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
