<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Somak Aditya</title>
    <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Somak Aditya</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Explicit Reasoning over End-to-End Neural Architectures</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/pslvqa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/pslvqa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many vision and language tasks require commonsense reasoning beyond data-driven image and natural language pro-
cessing. Here we adopt Visual Question Answering (VQA) as an example task, where a system is expected to answer a
question in natural language about an image. Current state-of-the-art systems attempted to solve the task using deep neural
architectures and achieved promising performance. However, the resulting systems are generally opaque and they struggle
in understanding questions for which extra knowledge is required. In this paper, we present an explicit reasoning layer on
top of a set of penultimate neural network based systems. The reasoning layer enables reasoning and answering questions
where additional knowledge is required, and at the same time provides an interpretable interface to the end users. Specif-
ically, the reasoning layer adopts a Probabilistic Soft Logic (PSL) based engine to reason over a basket of inputs: visual
relations, semantic parse of the question, and background ontological knowledge from word2vec and ConceptNet.
Experimental analysis of the answers and the key evidential predicates generated on the VQA dataset validate our approach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining Knowledge and Reasoning through Probabilistic Soft Logic for Image Puzzle Solving</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/riddles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/riddles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we explore a genre of puzzles (“image riddles”) which involves a set of images and a question.
Answering these puzzles require both capabilities involving visual detection (including object, activity recognition) and,
knowledge-based or commonsense reasoning. We compile a dataset of over 3k riddles where each riddle consists of 4 images and
a groundtruth answer. The annotations are validated using crowd-sourced evaluation. We also define an automatic evaluation
metric to track future progress. Our task bears similarity with the commonly known IQ tasks such as analogy solving,
sequence filling that are often used to test intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We develop a Probabilistic Reasoning-based approach that utilizes probabilistic commonsense knowledge to answer these
riddles with a reasonable accuracy. We demonstrate the results of our approach using both automatic and human evaluations.
Our approach achieves some promising results ($12\%$ improvement over baseline) for these riddles and provides a strong baseline for future attempts. We make
the entire dataset and related materials publicly available to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image Understanding using Vision and Reasoning through Scene Description Graph</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/sdg_cviu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/sdg_cviu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two of the fundamental tasks in image understanding using text are caption generation and visual question answering
[4, 72]. This work presents an intermediate knowledge structure that can be used for both tasks to obtain increased interpretability.
We call this knowledge structure Scene Description Graph (SDG), as it is a directed labeled graph, representing objects, actions,
regions, as well as their attributes, along with inferred concepts and semantic (from KM-Ontology [12]), ontological (i.e. superclass, hasProperty),
and spatial relations. Thereby a general architecture is proposed in which a system can represent both the content and underlying concepts of an
image using an SDG. The architecture is implemented using generic visual recognition techniques and commonsense reasoning to extract graphs from
images. The utility of the generated SDGs is demonstrated in the applications of image captioning, image retrieval, and through examples in
visual question answering. The experiments in this work show that the extracted graphs capture syntactic and semantic content of images
with reasonable accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DeepIU: An Architecture for Image Understanding</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/deepiu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/deepiu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Image Understanding is fundamental to systems that need to extract contents and infer concepts
from images. In this paper, we develop an architecture for understanding images, through which a
system can recognize the content and the underlying concepts of an image and, reason and answer
questions about both using a visual module, a reasoning module, and a commonsense knowledge
base. In this architecture, visual data combines with background knowledge and; iterates through
visual and reasoning modules to answer questions about an image or to generate a textual description
of an image. We first provide motivations of such a Deep Image Understanding architecture
and then, we describe the necessary components it should include. We also introduce our own
preliminary implementation of this architecture and empirically show how this more generic implementation
compares with a recent end-to-end Neural approach on specific applications. We
address the knowledge-representation challenge in such an architecture by representing an image
using a directed labeled graph (called Scene Description Graph). Our implementation uses generic
visual recognition techniques and commonsense reasoning to extract such graphs from images.
Our experiments show that the extracted graphs capture the syntactic and semantic content of an
image with reasonable accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Images to Sentences through Scene Description Graphs using Commonsense Reasoning and Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/sdg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/sdg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we propose the construction of linguistic
descriptions of images. This is achieved through the extraction
of scene description graphs (SDGs) from visual scenes
using an automatically constructed knowledge base. SDGs
are constructed using both vision and reasoning. Specifically,
commonsense reasoning1
is applied on (a) detections
obtained from existing perception methods on given
images, (b) a “commonsense” knowledge base constructed
using natural language processing of image annotations
and &amp;copy; lexical ontological knowledge from resources such
as WordNet. Amazon Mechanical Turk(AMT)-based evaluations
on Flickr8k, Flickr30k and MS-COCO datasets show
that in most cases, sentences auto-constructed from SDGs
obtained by our method give a more relevant and thorough
description of an image than a recent state-of-the-art image
caption based approach. Our Image-Sentence Alignment
Evaluation results are also comparable to that of the recent
state-of-the art approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Addressing the Winograd Schema Challenge-Building and Using a Semantic Parser and a Knowledge Hunting Module.</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/kparser/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/kparser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Concerned about the Turing test’s ability to correctly
evaluate if a system exhibits human-like intelligence,
the Winograd Schema Challenge (WSC)
has been proposed as an alternative. A Winograd
Schema consists of a sentence and a question. The
answers to the questions are intuitive for humans
but are designed to be difficult for machines, as
they require various forms of commonsense knowledge
about the sentence. In this paper we demonstrate
our progress towards addressing the WSC.
We present an approach that identifies the knowledge
needed to answer a challenge question, hunts
down that knowledge from text repositories, and
then reasons with them to come up with the answer.
In the process we develop a semantic parser
(&lt;a href=&#34;www.kparser.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;www.kparser.org&lt;/a&gt;). We show that our approach
works well with respect to a subset of Winograd
schemas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visual common-sense for scene understanding using perception, semantic parsing and reasoning.</title>
      <link>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/common-sense/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityasomak.github.io/publication/common-sense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we explore the use of visual commonsense
knowledge and other kinds of knowledge (such as
domain knowledge, background knowledge, linguistic
knowledge) for scene understanding. In particular, we
combine visual processing with techniques from natural
language understanding (especially semantic parsing),
common-sense reasoning and knowledge representation
and reasoning to improve visual perception to reason
about finer aspects of activities&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
